(intriguing music)
- [Instructor] Hello.
In this video we will discuss preferences.
Preferences are a term
we use, economists use
to denote, in a sense, consumers' brains.
So consumers' brains generate, of course,
preferences, desires, intentions,
levels of satisfaction,
and all that is comprised, in a sense,
in this broader term we call preferences.
Economists, we assume for simplicity,
that the consumer knows
how different options,
how different decisions
will impact their well-being
and that will be able to
choose the best one among those
that are available to him or her.
There are many ways to
represent preferences.
Imagine we have three
options, apple, banana, mango
and in this case, if there
are only three options,
apple, banana and mango, some consumer,
our hypothetical consumer,
prefers apple first,
but if it's between mango and banana,
this consumer prefers mango.
So the arrows have a complete description
of this consumer's preferences.
When it's apple versus banana, it's apple.
When it's mango versus apple, it's apple.
And when it's mango
versus banana, it's mango.
So again, arrows are description,
full description of this person,
of this consumer's preferences.
Different consumers could
have different preferences
and the consumer there at the top left,
this consumer prefers banana
over the other fruits.
The consumer that is at the
bottom is the previous consumer
that prefers apple to
the other two fruits.
And the interesting,
more peculiar consumer,
top right, prefers apple
when compared to banana,
prefers mango when mango
is compared to banana
and prefers banana when mango
and banana are to be contrasted.
This last case is what
we call in economics
an inconsistent consumer,
because it does not have
one single best option
in this simple universe of three fruits
and instead has inconsistent,
intransitive or cyclic preferences.
Arrows, however, are not the only way
in which we can represent preferences.
It is typically better to
represent preferences in ranking.
For example, if I am the consumer
that prefers banana over
the other two fruits,
I will have banana as my first option.
If there are other
fruits in consideration,
I could have considered mango.
The next position in this example,
it will be the third position,
assuming that there are other
fruits in the possibility
and apple would be my
fifth favorite fruit.
So ranking order also can
represent preferences,
not only arrows as we were saying before.
But there is a third way,
which is actually the way we will discuss
and we will use pretty much
for most of this class,
which is satisfaction levels
that we will call later utility level.
So it could be that if
I prefer banana most,
then I will give the
highest satisfaction level,
let's say in this case 10
and I will have smaller
or lower satisfaction
levels to the other options.
For example, mango will receive eight
and apple will receive six.
Let us now do some notation.
So we will use some notation to simplify
some of the math we will
discuss in the examples.
But in general, it's good to
know how the economist language
or logical and mathematical
language operates
to be able to read some of the discussion
in the textbook and outside.
So the first important
notation we need to learn today
is about how we write or how
we denote strict preferences.
We're gonna denote strict
preferences with a symbol.
For example, if we want to say x
is strictly more preferred than y,
it's gonna be written in this thing
that is right now in a light blue frame.
If we want to denote weak preference,
meaning, saying for example,
x is as least as preferred as y,
then we will have this similar symbol,
but with one squiggly thin below
as it is now highlighted on the screen.
If we instead want to denote indifference,
we will use this tilde symbol
and this tilde symbol
represents the statement,
x is equally preferred as y.
Now we're going to
discuss some assumptions
that we economists impose or have
for the preference relations
and in general, for consumers' choice.
The first assumption,
it's called completeness.
Completeness is, in colloquial terms,
is the idea that the
consumer, our consumer,
is always able to answer
a preference question.
What is a preference question?
A preference question
is a question such that,
do you prefer iPhone or Samsung Galaxy?
Do you prefer apple or banana?
Those are preference questions
and completeness assumption
says that or states
that the consumer is always
able to answer something,
meaning saying, "I prefer
iPhone to Samsung Galaxy,"
or, "I prefer Samsung Galaxy to iPhone,"
or, "I am indifferent between those two."
In simplified terms, this
is equivalent to say,
the consumer should be able to say always,
whether x is at least as good
or option x is at least
as good as option Y
or the opposite or the converse statement,
which is that y is at
least as good as option x.
So the ability of the consumer to be able
to answer the question with this or this
is the assumption of completeness,
the consumer is always able to say.
So students sometimes ask me, say,
"Wait, that sounds very broad.
I mean, I don't see a situation
in which you will not
satisfy completeness."
And I'll give you a simple example
of how we would not satisfy completeness.
Suppose I ask you, "Do you prefer
two burritos or two slices of pizza?"
And you tell me like, "I don't now."
So you don't tell me, "I'm indifferent,"
you don't tell me, "I
prefer this to that,"
or, "That to this," you
tell me, "I don't know.
I do not know how to answer
that preference question."
If you really do not know
how to answer that question,
then you indeed are violating
the assumption of completeness.
So in our words, in
economics, completeness means
that we always assume that
the consumer always knows
something about its preferences
to be able to say something regarding
or along the lines of,
"I prefer this to that
or that to this or those are indifferent."
The next assumption and possibly,
the most important assumption,
it's called transitivity.
Transitivity is a consistency assumption.
It's an assumption that economists have
to provide
our morals with consistent
rational agents.
It is true that not everyone is rational,
but it's also true that most people
or a large portion of the populations
are relatively rational.
So transitivity consistency,
which is related to rationality
is a very important
assumption in that regard.
But what exactly is it?
What exactly transitivity assumption is?
So in the transitivity assumption,
we will rule out that consumers
have cyclic preferences.
How do we do that?
We say, suppose there are three goods.
Or sorry, suppose there are three options.
You can take three different options.
They can be three different bundles
or they can be three
different fruits or something.
There are three different choice options.
If we denote these three options as x,
whoops, I couldn't highlight, but okay.
If we denote these three
options are x, y and z,
we should have that always
the following statement holds.
If x is at least as good as y
and y is at least as good as z,
then it must be that x is
also at least as good as z.
So let's actually do, sorry about that.
Let's actually do some example.
So suppose let's say that x is the iPhone
and y is Samsung Galaxy
and z is, let's say, a Nokia 900.
Suppose this consumer
weakly prefers x to y,
meaning iPhone to the Samsung Galaxy,
and then also prefers the
Samsung Galaxy to the Nokia 900,
it must be that the iPhone
is also weakly preferred to the Nokia 900.
So if this is correct,
if this is indeed what happens,
then we say, then transitivity assumption,
transitivity, holds.
So that is a simple
assumption, a simple example.
Now let's move on to the next assumption.
The next assumption is,
we call it, monotonicity
or simply more is better.
This assumption of
monotonicity or more is better
is simply saying that if
everything is the same
between two bundles,
except in one of them,
there is more of one of the goods,
then the one bundle that
has more of one of the goods
is strictly preferred to the order bundle.
So here's an example.
Suppose we have the bundle 5, 20,
Five ounces of coffee
and 20 cups of orange juice, let's say.
So five ounces of coffee
and 20 cups of orange juice.
Suppose now we have
slightly different bundle
that has 5.01 ounces of coffee
and still 20 cups of orange juice.
We will assume that
just the fact of having
slightly more of one of the goods,
of at least of one of the goods,
then will give the second bundle,
the one that has a bit more coffee,
the property to be strictly prefer
over the original or the initial bundle.
If a consumer preference
is word like this,
then we say that this consumer satisfy
the more is better or
monotonicity assumption.
So let me ask you a
couple of questions here.
So first question,
if the assumption of monotonicity holds,
which bundle is preferred, D or C?
D as in duck or C as in cat?
I hope you answered this correctly.
The answer is D, because in D,
we have not only more of one good,
we have more of both goods
with respect to C, so that is better.
Let's move, for example E
here, right to the border
and ask what would be the
comparison between E and C?
And the answer would be E
would be strictly prefer to C,
because although it might have
the same amount of good two,
it has more of good one.
And similar, you could
ask, what is the relation
between C versus B under
the monotonicity assumption?
And the answer would be that,
I'll give you a second to think about.
The answer would be that we don't know.
The monotonicity assumption
does not tell anything
about between C and B.
It does tell things about
D versus C, E versus C.
Monotonicity assumption does not solve
all the ranking of preferences.
Just gives you some of those comparisons
and in this case, it does
answer the comparison
between D and C because
D has more of everything.
It helps you with comparing E and C,
because E has more of one good
and the same of the other
good with respect to bundle C,
but does not rank the
order between A, B and C.
Because between B and C, for example,
indeed B has more than one of the goods,
but has less of the other,
so we cannot apply the same logic
as we did between D and C.
(intriguing music)